today we're going to be talking about
continuous integration something that
most software projects should be using
now for those of you who don't know
continuous integration or CI as it's
often referred to is the process of
continually integrating your code during
development now this might not make much
sense but what it essentially is is
build automation and testing to cut a
long story short in a software project
where multiple developers across
multiple different platforms are all
working on that project and continually
updating that code a lot of things can
go wrong someone for example might not
compile their code on all platforms or
in all configurations and as a result it
might completely break the build for
other developers or it just might
basically contribute bugs
additionally some bugs might not be
caught through a compilation error I
mean I think it's pretty reasonable to
expect someone to first compile their
code before they actually committed
especially if if it's a serious software
project however a lot of bugs obviously
manifest themselves at runtime and they
might only occur on specific Hardware on
a specific platform or their specific
configuration it's really not that
feasible for a developer to sit down and
have to spend like an hour testing
everything because they would probably
rather be working on something else in
fact you need them to be working on
something else so obviously some
problems can only be caught during
runtime by potentially using unit tests
or some kind of testing framework that
you probably integrated into the project
to make sure that everything is running
correctly but it's quite common for you
to want to run that on multiple
platforms multiple configurations all of
that stuff if that burden falls on to
the developer instead of a developer
working on actually you know a software
engineering and actually programming
more code and fixing other bugs they're
going to be stuck doing all of the
testing now that is not ideal and that's
where continuous integration comes in it
can help us automate that entire process
of making sure that the code compiles on
all platforms in all configurations for
everyone and then also run some basic
tests or any kind of automation tests
that your heart desires that you've
actually created to make sure that
everything is a plus plus this is
definitely one of those things that you
don't think you need until you realize
that everything just just getting out of
hand if we completely dumb this down
true what it is at its core basically
what we want to be able to do is build
our code after every commit that we make
and then also maybe run the application
to just see does it run without crashing
what's the output potentially and that's
what we're going to be doing today we're
going to be setting up a C++ project so
that we can automatically build and then
test our application every time a new
commit is pushed to get her and this is
getting really bright think maybe if I
just move this over here we're going to
dynamically change the set and
everything's gonna be a plus plus
because it needs to because I need to
get this video done otherwise my family
is going to starve so we're gonna use
Jenkins today as our continuous
integration environment
Jenkins is completely free and
open-source I'll leave a link in
description below for you guys to check
it out it's also something that we used
on a number of projects at EA so I quite
like it you can just run Jenkins on any
computer really you could run it on the
computer that used to develop all of
your code however typically you'd set it
up on a server because you would want it
to be running 24/7 and so I partnered
with Leonard for this video to make all
of this happen now what's Leonard I hear
you ask well you know it provides Linux
servers that make it easy for you to
host your app side or project in the
cloud if it runs on Linux
it runs on Leonard so if you need a host
like a website or a game server or set
up a CI machine like we're doing today
in this video Leonard has you covered
they have data centers all around the
world which means that you can set up a
server in a location that is like
geographically close to you which means
that you'll get that low latency and
you'll get the fastest speeds possible
best of all in ER it comes with 24/7
support that is a hundred percent
managed by humans that's really
important in case you need some help
they have got your back I want to thank
Lynn ardour for sponsoring this video
making all of this possible I'll show
you guys how to set up an actual lynyrd
server so that we can get our Jenkins
running on that and just how easy it is
to set up Jenkins with Leonard and Linda
have been nice enough to give you guys
$20 credit on a newly noted account more
on that later now a really basic staple
sauce program that I've written here and
I'll take you guys through that in a
minute
but really the first step here is to set
up something called a Jenkins file so
that we can actually tell Jenkins what
it is we wanted to do with our project
so here we have our repository inside a
bunch and this is just a really simple
simple sauce project as you'll see in a
minute so let me just take you through
the repository and show you what we've
got here so first off there's this pre
make five that lower file this is just a
script for pre make so that we can
actually construct our project files
will get Jenkins to automatically do all
of that stuff for us and that's why
inside their scripts directory we've got
this Linux build SH file this script
simply runs pre make to generate make
files for us and once we've got those
make files we can call make to actually
compile our project we've also got this
Linux run of SH file this script here
just runs our hello world program now if
we go back to our main repository folder
you'll see this hello world directory
inside there inside source we have this
hello world dot CPP file and you'll see
that like that's it this is as simple as
it gets really we just have a hello
world program here and so finally we
have this Jenkins file in our root
repository this is this is the important
file this is what tells Jenkins what on
earth to do with our project so the way
that this works is it's just a text
files divided into stages here we have
this build stage and this test stage so
over here in the build stage this is
what Jenkins needs to do to build our
project so you can see here that there
are multiple steps here and they're all
just really commands we're just echoing
out building into the command line so we
can see it and we're marking our Linux
build script as executable it's
important to note here that by this
stage Jenkins has already checked out
our repository so we've got this we've
cloned the repository and now we're able
to obviously run the script files that
we've got within the repository and we
do that by first marking them as
executable here and then just running
them then we've got this archive
artifacts part this is what actually
saves the build program as an artifact
so that we can then later run this
because you can see that the next stage
is test this is the testing stage and
what happens here is we again mark the
run script this time as executable so
that we can run it and then we run it
and this runs our program
so that's it that's really all there is
to it now we have a project and a
Jenkins file which instructs Jenkins how
to build and test our project now let's
pop over to lynyrd and take a look at
how we can actually set up a new server
and install Jenkins the first thing
we'll need to do is create some kind of
server to run our Jenkins instance
Leonard makes this really easy all we
need to do is click on one-click apps
select Jenkins and then choose our
region and Leonard plan this first one
should be fine for our needs we can give
it a name and a root password and that's
it we're done
Leonard is now automatically going to
allocate a server for us and install
Jenkins on it so we're ready to go it's
that easy and that's one of the things
that I love about Leonard it's so easy
to get going because I don't want to
spend time setting up server stuff I
want to spend time actually using my
server to do the things I got the server
for to gain access to our servers
command line we can either SSH in or we
can just use this console built into
Leonard's website once Leonard has
finished installing Jenkins for us we
can simply navigate our browser to our
server's IP address and finish the
Jenkins setup process you can see that
now Jenkins is in fact up and running
and it's asking us to retrieve the root
password from our file so let's go ahead
and do that using the command line we'll
plug in that password that we retrieved
and now Jenkins is unlocked and we can
continue on with the setup process I was
going to select Install suggested
plugins but if you like you can
customize which plugins actually get
installed once Jenkins has finished
installing all of our plugins we'll need
to create our first admin user I'll just
fill in these details here and click
Save and continue I'll leave this URL
here as is and that's it Jenkins is
ready we can now start using Jenkins now
on a fresh Jenkins install one of the
things that you might want to do is
install blue ocean blue ocean is just a
kind of newer more modern looking UI for
Jenkins this is completely optional you
don't really have to do this and in fact
I tend to kind of switch between the two
depending on what task I'm doing but I'm
going to install blue ocean and show you
what that's like so we'll select a blue
ocean aggregator here and just click
install without restart once that's done
we can just click open blue ocean and
then let's create our first pipeline a
pipeline is going to be the actual
continuous integration automation that
we've been talking about our goal is to
build and then test our project let's
hook this up automatically through
github now to do that we're going to
have to create a github access token so
let's
over to github and set that up in our
github profile settings I'm going to
click on developer settings and then
personal access tokens I'm then gonna
click generate new token and I'll give
it the name Jenkins example will give it
full repository access full control of
repository hooks and I'll also let it
read our user profile data and email
addresses this is important for Jenkins
because it requires it I'll click
generate token and that's it we've now
got a token now I can copy and paste
this into Jenkins without showing you
what it is of course and I'll click
connect I'll select the organization
that contains my repository and then the
actual repository and that's it you can
see the Jenkins is immediately going to
try and execute our pipeline by trying
to clean the repository and then do
whatever our jenkins file says let's
click on this run here to see what
exactly Jenkins is doing and oh you can
see that it failed let's see what went
wrong so scrolling through all this code
here you can see that it cannot run
program git and it says no such file or
directory that's because our server
doesn't actually have git installed and
it needs get so that it can clone the
repository let's go back to our service
command line and install git we're
already logged in as root here so no
need to type sudo I'll just type in
apt-get install git once that's done and
while we've still got our command line
open let's install everything else that
we'll need we'll need to install make
and then G plus plus so that we can
actually compile our code once our
server finishes installing everything
let's go back to Jenkins and we'll just
click this rerun button here this is
going to rerun this specific run meaning
it's not going to check out a different
commit or anything is literally just
going to rerun what just happened all
right check out from version control
succeeded and you can see everything
else succeeded as well awesome sorry
about that you can see here that there
are two phases to our pipeline we've got
the build that passed in two seconds and
then the tests that pass in one second
if we drop down this Linux run script
you can see the output of our script
which says hello world
so our program ran successfully yay and
going back to our list of runs you can
see that this has a green checkmark
status everything succeeded and our
project is in fact sunny let's get out
of blue ocean and see what regular
Jenkins looks like so we're inside
Jenkins example let's click on master
if we click build now what's gonna
happen is Jenkins is actually going to
retrieve the latest commits it's gonna
rerun that whole clone process and
execute our pipeline
let's see if that works out let's click
on this specific run to get more
information about it you can see here
that it's already finished running this
and we do in fact have a build artifact
that we chose to keep from our build
which is the hello world program this is
literally the Linux program that we can
well download and run on Linux if I
click it is just going to download it we
can also look at our console output
which is just a kind of less formatted
less sorted version of what we saw in
blue ocean you can see that it's built
it and then has run it here's our hello
world output if we flip back to our
github repository you can see that in
fact our last commit was successful all
checks have been passed because Jenkins
automatically reflects that data back to
github so that's super useful now the
only issue here is that at the moment we
have to manually click build now if we
want to actually build the latest
commits in our repository but what we
can actually do is set up a web hook so
that every time that we commit Jenkins
will automatically run a build on that
latest commit let's click on our
repository settings and then web hooks
and unless add a web hook now to set up
this web hook with Jenkins we just need
to drop in the URL of our server and
then add four slash github - web hook
we'll change the content type to be JSON
and we can leave the secret blank
because we have no secrets make sure
that pushes is selected here under the
individual events and that's it let's
click add web hook now let's go back to
Jenkins and we'll open blue ocean and
we'll just keep this view here with all
of our builds open so that when we
commit something new we can see if it
worked or not so going back to our Linux
computer now let's go into the
repository and change something I'll go
into that HelloWorld source file and
I'll change it to say hello Jenkins
instead of hello world once we've done
that let's commit this we'll go to our
terminal let's just check out get status
ok cool we've got that changed file and
it's the only file that's changed inside
this repository so let's go ahead and
add it and then we'll commit it I'll
just set the message to be updated
program once we've done that let's push
it to github
you can say that as soon as we've pushed
and you commit to the repository Jenkins
has received this push event branch
master and it's already running our
pipeline that was honestly seconds after
that push was actually made and you can
see that a few seconds later six seconds
later it's all completed successfully
and our get message has come through
here updated program so let's click on
it and see what the result was and you
can see that our output is in fact hello
Jenkins all of our new changes have come
through and run successfully so
hopefully that gave you guys an idea of
how you can actually set up CI for your
project so that you're continually
working in a stable environment now we
did use linux completely for our whole
environment today but you can definitely
apply this to multiple platforms that's
kind of the whole point it's very
popular of course for applications these
days true target multiple platforms but
if I'm working on Windows using Visual
Studio but my app also runs on like a
mobile device or Mac or Linux I don't
want to have to continually just open up
that computer and run all the tests and
actually make sure that my code compiles
on clang and not just em SVC I want CI
to do that for me and that's one of the
really strong benefits of setting
something like this up anyway that's
probably a story for another video I
hope you guys enjoyed this video if you
did please hit that like button a huge
thank you again to Leonard for
sponsoring this video you guys can try
later it out for yourselves there's a
link in the description to get $20
credit toward a new Lonard account check
it out and let me know what you think
you can use that credit to try out
Leonard's growing list of applications
such as setting up a Jenkins server like
I did in this video we can really use it
to host any projects you like online
give them a shot and let me know what
you guys think and I will see you next
time goodbye
[Music]
you